Here are two women. In the morning,
ở đây là có hai người phụ nữ buổi sáng
people are praying to the Bodhi tree
người ta th bồ
[music].
[âm nhạc]
Look here, dear friends, this flower and other
đề đây các đại hữ nhìn này Hoa này các
things to fight against the Bodhi tree. That's one of
thứ để chống C bồ đề đấy đấy một trong
the symbols of Buddhism and one
những biểu tượng của phật giáo và một
of the symbols of the Buddha. The
trong biểu tượng của Đức Phật là cây bồ
Buddha taught that wherever you see a Bodhi tree, you see the
đề Đức Phật đã dạy là ở đâu thấy cây bồ
Buddha. Wherever you see a Bodhi tree, there is the Buddha.
đề là thấy Đức Phật thấy cây bồ đề thì ở
So, in India, they have a
th cho nên là ở người dân Ấn Độ họ gì
very good tradition of culture and religion. They are closely connected to
thống tông l rất là tốt nhám liền sang
their beliefs.
với lại bên bên tính ngưỡng của họ tính
Their religion
ngưỡng của họ là đạo h Đạo giáo của họ
is Hinduism. If it's
thí ngn của họ là đạo Hindu Nếu mà đạo
Hinduism, they are also closely associated with
Hindu thì họ cũng gắn liền với lại đạo
Buddhism, just like in our country.
Phật giống như ở bên chúng ta các cái
Our religions also worship the
đạo tín ngưỡng của chúng ta cũng thờ
Buddha. It is also closely associated with the
Phật ở bên trên ấ nó cũng gắn liền với
Buddha. Dear friends, do you
Đức Phật quý Đạ Hữu đấy có quý Đạ Hữu
see? The Buddha taught that the
thế hay không thấy nhá Đức Phật dạy cây
Bodhi tree is a symbol of the Buddha, so
bồ đề là biểu tượng của đức Phật cho nên
whoever prays to the Bodhi tree is considered to be praying to the
là ai lễ cây bồ đề cũng coi như là lễ
Buddha. And here,
Phật Và ở đây thì họ cầu nguyện như thế
they pray in accordance with the spirit of the
là họ cầu nguyện đúng với tinh thần của
Buddha. They come here.  At the Bodhi tree, they
đức Phật đấy họ đến chỗ cội cây bồ đề họ
pray for the liberation of their loved ones.
cầu nguyện cho người thân của họ được
If a family
siêu thoát nếu như là trong gia đình có
member has recently passed away, they go to the
người thân mới mất thì họ đến chỗ cội
Bodhi tree to pray for their loved one's liberation.
cây bồ đề để họ cầu nguyện cho người
After that, they
thân được siêu thoát sau rồi họ lại đến
pray for health under the Bodhi tree.
cầu nguyện sức khỏe ở dưới cội cây bồ đề
If they pray, they pray to the
đấy nếu có cầu nguyện thì cầu nguyện từ
saints, which is
nơi các bậc thánh hay đấy các quý đại ý
very beautiful. They light incense and pray,
ạ rất là hay họ thắp hương cầu nguyện
then circumambulate the Bodhi tree,
xong họ đi nhiễu xung quanh cây bồ đề đi
hoping that all these people will
đề nguyện mong tất cả những người này
eventually become disciples of the Buddha.
rồi sau cũng thành đệ tử phật thôi bây
Now they have become disciples of the Buddha, although they
giờ đã thành đệ tử Phật rồi Tuy rằng
don't know it yet, dear friends. Why was
chưa biết thôi các quý Đạ Hữu ạ Tại sao
the Buddha born in India? Because
Đức Phật sinh ra ở đất nước Ấn Độ vì đất
India is a very religious country,
nước Ấn Độ là một đất rất là tín ngưỡng
and they greatly respect the symbols
thế và họ rất là kính các cái biểu tượng
of the Buddha because they consider him
của đức Phật bởi vì là họ coi Đức Phật
a deity. Therefore,
là một vị thần của họ thế thì nhân duyên
this karmic connection means that all
này thôi thì sau này tất cả những người
these people will eventually follow the true Dharma. Do you
này rồi sẽ tu theo chánh pháp thôi các
see the Buddha's compassion? It's truly
quý Đại Hữu thấy lòng từ của Đức Phật
amazing. He
tuyệt vời chưa rất là tuyệt vời Ngài
knew where he was born to receive lasting blessings, and
biết là sinh ra ở đâu thì được độ lâu
his teachings would be beautiful
dài giáo pháp của ngài thì được tốt đẹp
and effective.  By sowing the seeds of Dharma for the majority of sentient beings,
và gieo Duyên được số đông cho chúng
all those who follow Hinduism
sinh tất cả những người theo đạo Hindu
will later become Buddhists, dear fellow practitioners. Is
này rồi sau sẽ thành phật tử hết các quý
n't that wonderful? It must be
đạo hữu ạ rất là hoan hỉ không rất là
said that the wisdom and compassion
hoan hỉ phải nói là trí tuệ và lòng từ
of the Buddha are truly amazing, because it's
của Đức Phật rất là tuyệt vời bởi vì
impossible for everyone to immediately connect
không thể nào mà ai cũng kết duyên được
with the true Dharma. It must be done gradually, step by step,
với chánh pháp ngay đâu cũng phải đi từ
guiding them step by step,
từ từng bước một dẫn dắt từng bước từng
like trying to emerge from a
bước một giống như là mình muốn đi từ
dense forest. Even though we can see the
rừng rậm đi ra Tuy rằng mình nhìn ra bên
outside world, we still have to walk
ngoài kia rồi nhưng mà cũng phải đi từ
slowly to get out of the dense forest, dear
từ mới ra được khỏi khu rừng rậm các quý
practitioners. Therefore, the compassion
Đạ Hữu thấy không Thế cho nên lòng từ
of the Buddha is truly wonderful. In
của Đức Phật là rất là tuyệt vời giữa
a forest of false views, the
một cái rừng Tà kiến như thế nhưng đức
Buddha knew which path to choose to
phật biết cho chọn tà kiến là ở môn nào
guide them away from false views and
có thể dẫn dắt họ ra khỏi tà kiến dẫn
gradually lead them into Buddhism. The
dắt dần họ vào đạo Phật được thì chính
Buddha himself went to Brahmanism. Is
Đức Phật đã đến Đạo Bà La Môn đó tuyệt
n't that wonderful, dear practitioners? It's truly
vời không các quý Đạ Hữu rất là tuyệt
wonderful. Therefore, all
vời cho nên tất cả những người đạo Bà la
those Brahmanists are very close to us Buddhists,
môn này rất là gần với lại phật tử chúng
as well as to the religious beliefs of
ta cũng như là đạo tín ngưỡng ở dân tộc
our nation. Even those who haven't yet fully embraced
ta ấ những người tuy rằng Chưa hẳn theo
Buddhism, before they do so...  The ceremony of
đạo Phật Nhưng trước khi họ làm lễ dì h
Nam Mô A Di Đà (Homage to Amitabha Buddha)... So gradually, in
Nam Mô A Di Đà pht Thế là dần dần sau
future lives, will we also become Buddhists,
rồi Các Kiếp sau cũng thành phật tử hay
or not, esteemed Great Friends? In the past,
chưa các quý Đại Hữu hay không hồi xưa
we also held wrong views, even in
chúng ta cũng tà kiến thế ngay trong
this life, at the beginning of our lives, we didn't hold wrong views. Then in
kiếp này đầu đời chúng ta chả tà kiến
other lives,
Thế các kiếp khác cũng phải tà kiến
we will also hold wrong views. But this kind of wrong view is due to a connection with the Buddha. There are many kinds of wrong views, and even those that destroy the Buddha's teachings, people
diệt giáo pháp của Phật thì người ta
also have a connection from afar, and gradually, gradually,
cũng có duyên xa xa xong dần dần dần dần
gradually, they come to
dần dần mới vào đến các cái tà kiến mà
respect the Buddha, and only then do they come to true
kính đức Phật xong rồi mới vào đến kiến
understanding. Great Friends, that's interesting! The Buddha has many inconceivable teachings, and this is
nhiều pháp Bất Khả tư nghì thì đây là
one of the inconceivable teachings that connects and saves sentient
một trong cái pháp kết duyên độ cho
beings. The esteemed Great Friends are
chúng sinh Bất Khả tươ nghỉ Quý đợ hiện
very wonderful. The Buddha said
rất là tuyệt vời thể nào mà Đức Phật nói
that the symbol of the Buddha is the Bodhi tree.
là biểu tượng của Đức Phật là cây bồ đề
Whoever worships the Bodhi tree is considered to be worshiping the
ai lễ cây bồ đề là coi như là lễ đức
Buddha. It's very wonderful.
phật đấy rất là tuyệt vời
[Music]
[âm nhạc]